Guide to the Jay Rutherfurd papers, 1887-1995
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Jay Rutherfurd papers 1887-1995
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Rutherfurd, Jay
8.0 Linear Feet Approx. 2613 Items
Broadcast journalist, businessman, and resident of Palm Beach (Palm Beach Co.), Fla.
These papers are comprised primarily of correspondence, clippings, essays, and articles related to the subjects Rutherfurd covered during his career as a broadcast journalist. Topics reflect his interest in diplomacy, journalism, and U.S. foreign relations since 1961. Much of the material documents the career of Angier Biddle Duke, a Rutherfurd family friend who served in the diplomatic corps during the Kennedy and Johnson administrations. Other material reflects the instrumental role Rutherfurd played in the creation of Duke University's Living History Program. The collection also contains more than 53 audiocassettes, two videocassettes, scripts, and filmed interviews (late 1960s to 1980s) with prominent individuals, as well as recordings of TV news segments and radio shows.
In addition, the collection contains Rutherfurd family photographs, diaries, scrapbooks, legal papers, and a genealogy, as well as drafts of Jay Rutherfurd's memoir and miscellany. Individuals represented in these materials include John F. Kennedy, Lyndon B. Johnson, Richard Nixon, Haile Selassie, King Hussein of Jordan, Tito, Prince Juan Carlos of Spain, Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, Robin Chandler Lynn Duke, Jacques Fray, Rafael Calvo, Stanton Griffis, Earl E. T. Smith, Ottis Pike, Lucius Clay, Averell Harriman, Henry Kissinger, John Sherman Cooper, Stanton Griffis, Terry Sanford, Willy Brandt, Ellsworth Bunker, and Ryoichi Sasakawa, as well as other celebrities and heads of state. These materials also document Jay Rutherfurd's trips to Morocco, Southeast Asia, Nepal, the Panama Canal Zone, the People's Republic of China, Iran, and the Middle East, as well as the social life of Southampton, N.Y., and Palm Beach, Florida.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Jay Rutherfurd Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1967 to 1996.
Collection Overview
The papers of Jay Rutherfurd are comprised primarily of correspondence, clippings, essays, and articles related to the subjects Rutherfurd covered during his career as a broadcast journalist. Topics reflect his interest in diplomacy, journalism, and U.S. foreign relations since 1961. Much of the material documents the career of Angier Biddle Duke, a Rutherfurd family friend who served in the diplomatic corps during the Kennedy and Johnson administrations. Other material reflects the instrumental role Rutherfurd played in the creation of Duke University's Living History Program. The collection features more than 53 audiocassettes, two videocassettes, scripts, and filmed interviews (late 1960s to 1980s) with prominent individuals, as well as recordings of TV news segments and radio shows.
In addition, the collection contains Rutherfurd family photographs, diaries, scrapbooks, legal papers, and a genealogy, as well as drafts of Jay Rutherfurd's memoir and miscellany. Individuals represented in these materials include John F. Kennedy, Lyndon B. Johnson, Richard Nixon, Haile Selassie, King Hussein of Jordan, Tito, Prince Juan Carlos of Spain, Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, Robin Chandler Lynn Duke, Jacques Fray, Rafael Calvo, Stanton Griffis, Earl E. T. Smith, Ottis Pike, Lucius Clay, Averell Harriman, Henry Kissinger, John Sherman Cooper, Stanton Griffis, Terry Sanford, Willy Brandt, Ellsworth Bunker, and Ryoichi Sasakawa, as well as other celebrities and heads of state. The material also documents Rutherfurd's trips to Morroco, Southeast Asia, Nepal, the Panama Canal Zone, the People's Republic of China, Iran, and the Middle East, as well as social life in Southampton, N.Y., and Palm Beach, Fla.
Original audiovisual recordings are closed to use; listening or viewing copies may need to be produced before contents can be accessed. Please consult with Research Services staff before coming to use this material.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Rutherfurd, Jay
Duke, Angier Biddle, 1915-1995
Duke, Robin Chandler Lynn
Duke family
Rutherfurd family
Duke University. Living History Program
Diplomacy -- History -- 20th century
Heads of state -- Pictorial works
United States -- Foreign relations -- 1945-1989
Photographs
Scrapbooks
Audiotapes
Audio cassettes
Videocassettes
Diaries
Contents of Collection
- Jay Rutherfurd Papers, 1887-1995, (29 boxes)
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - Correspondence, 1959-1970 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1971- (Box 2)
  - Printed materials (Box 3)
  - Writings (Box 4)
  - News broadcasts and dispatches (Box 5)
  - Photographs (Box 6)
  - Diaries (Box 7)
    Restrictions on the diaries were lifted in 2002.
  - Clippings (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook, 1974-1977 (Box 9)
  - Volumes (Box 10)
  - Volumes (Box 11)
  - Volumes (Box 12)
    War years with counterintelligence in Middle East reports are included.
  - Volumes (Box 13)
    Serge Obolensky book, "One Man in his Time"
  - Volumes (Box 14)
  - Middle East, miscellaneous, 1997 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous, The Insider's Newsletter (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous, audio visual project (Box 17)
  - Panama Canal Treaty, miscellaneous, 1977 (Box 18)
  - Middle East audiotapes, 1977 (Box 19)
  - Tape recordings (Box 20)
  - Tapes and negatives (Box 21)
  - Cassette tapes and negatives (Box 22)
  - Scrapbook (Box 23)
  - Photo album (Box 24)
  - Additions (unprocessed), 90/110, 91/115, 93/164 (Box 1)
  - Additions (unprocessed), 92/045, 93/286, 93/289 (Box 1)
  - Addition, 1986 (unprocessed) (Box 1)
  - Addition, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Addition, 1986 (Box 3)